so as a suitor here called the farmer
now on that occasion blasted ones
instructing exhorting inspiring
lightning the bhikkhus the Dhamma talk
concerning it on those bhikkhus were
listening to the done with eg a is
attending to it as a matter of vital
concern applying their whole minds to it
then it occurred have occurred to Mara
the evil one he says he got bottom up is
instructing the bhikkhus let me approach
the ascetic of cotton in order to
confound him then mara the evil world
manifested himself in the form of the
farmer carrying a large pile on his
shoulder holding a large go stick with
her - I was wearing Temple garments his
feats made with nod he approached the
Blessed One and said to him maybe you've
seen oxen ascetic what a rock Centene
you evil what okay the eye is mine the
eye is mine ascetic forms a mine my
contact and its base of consciousness
where can you go ascetic to escape from
me the year is mine ascetic sounds of
mine the nose is mine my body is mine
the mind is - ethic mental phenomena are
mine mine contact and its face the
consciousness are mine
where can you go ascetic to escape from
me and then the Buddha says the eye is
yours little one
norms are yours I contact a little base
of consciousness all yours but evil one
where there is no I no forms no eye
contact and its face of consciousness
there is no place for you there evil the
air is yours
the nose is yours
the tongue is yours the body is yours
mind is yours evil one phenomena hi
yours mine combat contact and its base
of consciousness are yours but evil one
where there is no mind no phenomena no
mind contact in its base of
consciousness there is no place for you
there
then the verse mara says that of which
they say it's mine and those who speak
in terms of mine if your mind exists
among these you won't escape me ascetic
that which they speak of is not mine I'm
not one of those who speak of mine you
should know those so everyone even my
path you will not see quite clearly
illustrates where the problem is
so the problem is not in the eye in the
sights the consciousness establish the
point it's not even in the pressure that
I exhibits
besides example on you the contact
usually it should say this contact
that's really a profession none of those
is a problem problem is regarding it is
mind problem is having the assumption of
ownership in regard to it and many other
occasions that's what will ascend it's
because you take that which belongs to
Mara murder does with you what he
pleases what is it it belongs to Mara I belongs
what is it it belongs to Mara I belongs
to Mara sites below tomorrow constant
from tomorrow knows and so on everything
else
so hydrogen escape Maura
how'd you then escape suffering without
destroying eyes sight sound smell taste
touches without avoiding contact without
giving into pressure without like to
deny pressure yeah and how how would
that be done how would you not take the
ownership because not taking ownership
you can own that ya attitude oh nothing
is mine yeah but if you reckon but if
you if you see like like the mother
saying here the Ark is yours then so if
you see that that which everything kind
of depends on
we're just seeing that spies cannot be
used sites but the only way to see that
correctly is to see that they cannot be
yours through your current and stake in
ownership that's the important point
crucial point so that's the crucial
point you need to see because si UD that
suit that the Buddha said I'm not the
one who says mine I don't use mine
people say Osama stop saying mine as if
just by don't say mine you somehow
transcend the mistaken ownership by
avoiding to label it but mine is the
state of mind as the same well says the
mind is there and it regards things as
belonging to to the to it so old it's a
mistake it's real as such so first you
have to accept it
ownership is there the you regard your
senses is yours sites displease you
sites they displease you basically you
regard your body is the basis of your
body the basis of your experience as
belonging to you so within that
ownership you then need to discern that
these things are actually impossible to
own not in response to your ownership so
ownership is a problem so I will go
around and keep telling myself that I
can own these things even if I want to
but the only reason you're doing that or
rather the reason you're doing that is
rooted in you trying to basically get
rid of the ownership and you own that
because you're acting out of the same
one ship you're affirming it your
craving for it
craving you against it craving is there
so accepting that there is ownership and
it's not a matter of choice because as
long as there is eyes there is ownership
as long as their sights there is
ownership of it so allowing that
ownership and you're yeah but to say
that it's dependent on so once once you
become skilled so to speak in no denying
ownership not acting blindly out of it
but seeing it for what it is
practicing restraint in regard to its
sure but allowing it to endure then you
can get to see what's within the
which is the basis necessary basis for
their ownership which cannot be on the
basis for that ownership what makes that
ownership possible the first place so
what is the necessary condition from the
ownership of eyes and sights like things
that please me I wanna I'm gonna go and
look at something agreeable what is it
what is what is the necessary basis for
that experience body the body exactly or
more specifically the eyes and things to
be looked at so say in half an hour
you want to go and I don't know watch a
parade see a movie whatever it is
something you want visually pleasing
Boyle so you have the prospect of
engaging with sights and you said you
know you accept it you get ready and you
start going whatever that is happening
but so you're already committed to that
and from the point of like even before
when you just decide to do it to engage
with the sights there is a necessary
basis there's a prospect of the sights
possibility they need to be there to
some extent or at least there is a
likelihood of them being there so your
entire project of planning to engage
making effort to engage with with a
sense object is fully within necessary
basis of those things necessary
container necessary dependence upon
those things and then you go there and
turns out the movies cancelled yet this
whole time you were acting as if it were
their telling to see that the necessary
basis doesn't matter how much you are in
control how many like you can afford a
ticket you have you can get there in
time you booked your space everything
all these things you can't control
are fully within the necessary basis of
things that fundamentally cannot be
controlled such as things get cancer
things get destroyed you die on the way
up there
so that might not be obvious under that
it's not just site sites that have the
eyes necessary bases any possible any
possibility yeah so on the level that's
why everything starts basically in stays
and maintains itself within the mind
enduring yeah so when you have the
prospect of going to see the movie there
is no movie present here it's just a
thought and you're not seeing any of
that but that thought is stance forward
your eyes are at the time as in that's
why all the senses the five senses meet
in the mind that's where they are
discerned and it may even be something
that's not attended to like consciously
attended to you know you like you people
make decisions to go watch a film
without and you don't need to sort of
analyze it I hope I die tonight so the
necessary condition for the mechanism no
you just whatever you're about to do you
see it as an a reason prospector than
yours and you can then exercise either
restraint or giving in to it if it's
wholesome you can do it if it's
unwholesome if it's rooted in desire if
it's rooted in distraction you restrain
yourself you don't do it either way
prospects will be in your mind for doing
this for doing that you cannot not do
anything you say I'm not doing anything
that you're doing so once you have sort
of a dedicated engagement to careless
engagement with prospects that are
rooted in desire then the ones that you
can do you then get to understand how
like basically the threshold where were
your commitment sort of overreaches so
to speak oh I need to do this that's
fine you don't necessarily need to be
emotionally invested in doing it and
then if thing changes before you have
completed it before you've done it the
way you wanted it or whichever way it
goes you won't be emotionally affected
because you never lost the perspective
that doesn't matter what you do it's fun
mentally rooted contained within the
basis within container that cannot be on
so the only way to arrive at through non
ownership of things is through ownership
through learning how to accept the
ownership and allow it to endure and not
blind the act towards it or try to get
rid of it it displeases because that's
another thing when you have disagreeable
experience affects you that's why you
are affected because it's yours you want
to get rid of the owning unpleasant
things oh I own this this is mine but
look it's it's turning really bad I'll
get rid of it I will stop owning it that
so the Buddha meant in brief suffering
is being United with what we don't want
and I saw that the separated from things
we want so owning things you don't want
and not owning things you want and
that's the root of every suffering what
you wanted what you don't want
so that's why I like the sensor strain
needs to come first because ownership is
there which means you're already acting
out of it so you need to stop acting out
of it in a sense they would perpetuate
that desire and anything unwholesome
it's rooted in it it's still one free
from the ownership but it will certainly
set up things to be understood as an
understanding ownership in that sense
that you're not emotionally invested in
it and that's the true ownership to go
through through lack of ownership it's
not like throwing away things you own
destroying them because then if that
were the case we'll say you just have to
pull your eyes out and you're free from
ownership of sights the true ownership
is not being pressured by those things
not owning the contact not being
contacted by them Mars has thought that
of which they say it's mine and those
who speak in terms of knowing if your
mind exists among these
so if there is absolutely no feeling
pressuring you manifested arising
whatever making you act on account of
what's there in your experience where
they wanted oh no want it you're not
owning it so that's always it also you
can use that as a as a criteria oh well
I'm an attached to this so if if you
were to change if it were to become
otherwise if you were to be taken away
without experience disagreeable feeling
they would then overwhelm my mind would
I put a basically suffer encounter that
if you're not sure means yes doubt means
yes we will suffer you have to be
absolutely clear it it and that to me
like you can you don't need to go and
lose these things you don't need to go
and watch a movie to know that you're
doing it out of desire
you already know it when the prospect
has a reason on the level of possibility
you don't need to go to see that the
movie stencil oh no the fact is you're
acting out of the desire so even if you
don't get to see the movie you still
acted out of the desire on the level of
your thought even if the think of cancer
then you didn't actually engage to the
extent you wants to engage you still
engage with it with the desire because
desire is not in those things it's on
the level of your mind
so saying then you can imagine things
that that out there to you dear to you
or or or things that are threatening to
you you don't need to go and engage with
them just think about it and you're
already either affected or not either
craving to be free from it are you
either clearly against it or caring for
more of it
just like the suta where they're in them
jatis would insanity says would you be
upset if fix took away all those yeah
because you don't care about yeah you're
absolutely have no emotional interest in
random twins yeah says well that's how
you should regard your body your eyes
but as i said certainly they're in the
beginning of that practice the attitude
will never keenan somebody comes in
either so then immediately you think
okay so on the ship is bad and yet
ownership is the root of suffering so
then whatever you do you will well in
the beginning you won't be able to see
it wherever you do will be an account of
trying to get rid of the ownership but
the only way to get rid of the ownership
is to accept it and understand it you
can't understand it you can keep trying
to get rid of it oh itself doesn't sell
purses it's a knob that's attached but
just throw things away just gives you a
stuff gives yourself you are not
understanding ownership because whenever
you face it you're just don't even wait
fun tonight
so you can do you just don't do this
thing that you used to do provide an
explanation for it they're not cheap
they're not they don't belong to you
anyways yes it's okay yeah the whole you
know sexual means of course the cake
because it's animal instincts
that's that's even more dishonest
basically but yeah I know but what I'm
saying like you must have abandoned that
attitude through your behavior even
before you can become aware of the
ownership on its own terms because
that's the point like people can read
and declared himself Buddhist and then
just say that nothing is real anyway
nothing nothing belongs to me I can do
whatever I want only if you're in
another hand the statement nothing
belongs to me is true so are you not
know thus you saying everything is anata
is false your own experience it's a lie
yeah yeah Oh wishful thinking usually
thank you sure based on the based on the
assumption that if I keep telling myself
this dishonest like you're lying to
yourself that same Lord can do these
things without attachment
if there is no attachment there is no
pressure and that's another that's
another suitor Buddha said sometimes I
asked monks to abandon some little
trifle thing something not so important
but it's still kind of an obstacle so
the Buddha would ask them to stop doing
that and then some monk said well look
this is nothing I can stop this whenever
I want and because of that he doesn't
stop it and he gets affected by it
because he didn't stop it stopping it
doesn't matter what you think about it
stopping it will for you not stopping it
won't for you so you think you can stop
it anytime then it's true you can't stop
it anytime here because of that hook you
don't stop it ahead of time and then
another monkey says oh this is trifle
this is little this is insignificant and
then he makes the effort and he stops it
he's free from it and then the simile
said that the first month the one who
doesn't stop it it's like a quail who is
who is sort of tethered by the ropes and
ropes and tiny little strings but the
crane is weak and that's more than
enough then to keep it up to keep it
high and the other one is like an
elephant they get styled by leather
straps and it's often when people say I can
and it's often when people say I can
stop this whenever I want but what you
can't want is to stop it yeah never you
want you can't want to want to stop it
yeah if you were to want to stop it and then
if you were to want to stop it and then
you could you stop it whenever you want
but you can't want to stop it and that's
why you end up not stopping it so yeah
like when people say oh I can have
sexual intercourse without being
attached that's ridiculous I mean not
just it would have said millions of
times that's impossible in the surface
but also like how can you even engage to
any extent of like physical pursuit of
sensuality without being pressured by
rights without accepting it without
acting out of it without and that's
already attachment that's already you're
acting out of cradle that's a simile of
the snake that's what it's a small
person because that one can engage in
sensual pleasures without sensual
decisions without perception substantial
design with desire that isn't possible
yeah that's what I'm saying so even
before you go and get to see the movie
or see the movies cancelled you've
already engaged with central aspect of
it by deciding to do it yet let's on the
level of the thought that's already
sensual perception so central perception
doesn't matter it is the actual movie or
of the thoughts of the possibility of
the movie perception of the visual
domain which is both actual and possible
is there basically it's an image it's an
immature habit which you've been crush
it yeah so you already accepted the
desire on the level of your thought and
that thought remains the during that's
the whole point if say you you desire of
the thoughts of your desire you accept
it then it disappears you wouldn't know
where to go what to do you wouldn't have
context for your action of seeking
such-and-such movie or or or
entertainment to a group of people or
fun that desire remains and that desire
makes every further engagement within it
to be within their desire so that's why
you can't necessarily judge things
externally whether this is always
designer this is not always design
sexually because it's always desire
killing it's always desire things are
basically clearly against the presets
are always rooted
but there are sometimes things that are
route 10 built-in desire internally but
not to always sometimes they're not
necessarily routine design but if you
were to only judge things externally
means to deal with his eye look he has
these possessions he's always attached
to it look he's eating he's always
craving for his food but you can
actually not accept desire on the level
of the thought and then even if you eat
none of those actions that follow would
well now they would be within
non-acceptance of desire and even if you
practice restraint
if you accept desire on the level of
thought and then restrain yourself
physically verbally you still within the
desire because that's where desire is
rooted so the level of accepting those
possibilities those images in your mind
like I want that I don't want that the
restraint is me so even if you're
restraining yourself yeah well like
restraint is necessary but yeah it will
still be within the desire and then when
the mind is uprooted from that desire
what other design is approved from the
mind thank you
keeping if you like Luke look at the
nice food he's eating there doesn't mean
he's attached and that's what the Buddha
said himself sometimes he gets those you
know queens and kings serving with their
own hands that the finest possible food
and then says after they know this are
in his mind he would sometimes it ball
full to the brim sometimes to balls to
the brim if he's hungry there is a
practical need for such amount of food
if he walked for 30 kilometres across be
her or something and there is absolute
no attachment but if you judge the food
the attachment by the amount of food you
eat then you will respect the Buddha
there's a whole suit about when that man
was praising the Lord his disciples in
little and eat sleep no
I was underneath for days and I would
sit in queen who would sell me herself
like to the brim full bowl of whatever
you could possibly imagine if they were
to respect me because of that they
wouldn't and then same with the Lord
rings and the medicines and so on
so the roots of the desire is the root
is in the root of ownership which is on
the level of your mind see if you were
like say practicing or maintaining
recollecting the context of death when
you have a thought I'm going to watch a
movie and in the back of mind you refuse
to abandon the context that you might
die within the next soundtrack puts any
central port movie company other people
would any of that would be able to make
it worthwhile if you think that you
might die next second no how can you
possibly accept further down the line
things that depend upon your life when
your life is in question
so that's why there is like if you
maintain that kind of perspective that
kind of rate collectiveness South you
then death you will abandon sensuality
the very least do you mean let the whole
so any let's say engaging with the film
watching yourself think we let this
think with practically you don't think
you're gonna die and you wanna watch
your film and you enjoy now just before
the movie somebody tells you I got you
doctors results yeah and you have 24
hours maybe most yeah would you watch
the same movie and spend three hours
watching it or even just you got six
months to live sure sure even six months
even less than later even less when
somebody reorders the importance of the
context for you would you then engage
with the movie it would be like you
would have no desire for it either so
the necessary basis for your desire is
lack of context and that's it you think
you can own the eyes
hi you think you own the eyes you are
the owner of the eyes you took that for
granted thus now let me find things that
will engage my eyes presently but
somebody tongue comes and tells you you
were gonna lose you're gonna lose
everything not just your eyes how can
you possibly care for random sight sound
smell taste tangents
so you don't want to wait for that to
happen because if you have a practice
beforehand it would be too late for you
to make a play so you want to start
basically regaining reclassifying
recollecting this perspective that is
there you are truly like the movie can
be cancelled or not but one thing for
sure you cannot avoid dying but that's
the thing your your enjoyment of the
film requires life to be there yeah
exactly it requires a kind of I'm gonna
find out what well but that's what means
the side is such other side Sydney
demise yeah so if there is no
persistence of functioning eyes sites
are meaningless and that's what that's
where life is resistance of senses their
living senses I'm alive senses of mine
does this life is mine I'm in control of
it so you need to do is stop ignoring
the fact that you already know that's
what like people used to say something
Oh be careful oh don't don't say that
don't say that cuz you said that you
might go blind or something yeah no but
you might you might get sick oh but you
must not say it because it makes me
afraid themselves with anxiety how could
that be possible if you're not truly
liable to it so it really reminds you of
anxiety and fear fear and anxiety are
the reminders of that which you are
liable to so when I say please don't
make me scared about you know that I'll
die or go blind and lose my senses means
just don't remind me of what I already
know but I am subjective and that's that
that's the core of the respect is stop
ignoring that by any means necessary
the divine messengers again it's not
like some quiet the inspiration of AI
everybody with that no it's recognizing
that doesn't matter what you do to what
extent for how long how many times
doesn't matter
you are live you are at any time subject
to death subject two to two
to change subject to loss basically then
time you're not in control of your own
basis of your own experience that's so
firstly reckon that's not was the first
step recognizing that your subjective
that's the first step and that's a step
within which every other step is
contained there is a suit on the search
I am this this is what I have have
subject who is subject to death
searching for something that is also
subjected what so I've got all this
death yeah subject to deafness yeah with
me Sonam is going search for other other
things that also yeah I'm ready
fulfilled it yeah so you so you're
saying I can recognize that you are
subject to loss your subjects well you
don't really let people what you just
described that that's not understanding
your subject to death that people might
say yeah I'm subject to death and then
you see what you're gonna do next if
your next move is within something
that's also subject to death this means
you're using that to basically distract
yourself from the fact that you're
subject to death so you're not really
staying on the level of I am subject to
death because if you are you would
genuinely lose the desire for any
further engagement down the line of
death it would be inconceivable so am i
okay I might fully turned away from
these things that are further within
death no means I haven't fully
understood what means being subject to
that means sorry that's what the sense
of urgency why am i and that becomes
apparent when you when you truly feel
that sense of urgency then you're
subject to death and then well I feel
this it's way too
threatening to unpleasant to too serious
to ignore so how can then I possibly go
in search further things that are within
that death but it's not it's not on the
level of just just reason it you can't
just reason it or rather people can
reason it which means it's going to be
rooted in you trying to avoid it or you
covering up the perspective through your
reasoning of it because practically
speaking it would be impossible to
engage with sense objects if you within
the context of death it's impossible so
then you reverse that and have a look am
i engaging or not yes means I cannot
turn at the same time thing that I am
established upon there the context of
death because I am engaging I am still
wanting these things now as I said the
truth so if you have 24 hours or even
less left to live and there is possible
way out from that perilous situation
then are there ways awaits for you why
would you choose finding the way out of
death or oh let me go watch this movie
and like make the most of my time that's
left it's it's it's awesome the choices
automatic that's whether the rule would
always say for whoever and literally
doesn't matter if the petition on our
hand whenever you do something whenever
you want something you do it because
it's deep down inside it is rooted in
your notion of my own well-being
oh it's that's you engage with desire
because these are is unpleasant
so to engage with it you try to get rid
of there the pain you engagement in
pursuit of our hardship because you
understood it underneath it all again
it's all its you're subjected to pain so
your own well-being is basically
overcoming pain it's just by what means
you do it is gonna make a bunch of pain
or free from pain so when it comes to
such a clear-cut choice death waits for
you possible escape or ignoring it the
choices automatic
because the only reason you've been
ignoring it before is because there was
the closest to your means of escape of
pain this quarter
this quarter
I thought to have if he weren't told
before that yes
oh yeah Eddie too dense but then many in
the Buddhist in the thought processes
why don't I seek that which is deathless
yeah why don't I seek the way out of her
death well the person that has developed
the context of death yeah then I think
back in the day people were much less
dishonest with himself so more of them
would have had that upon hearing the
Buddha now you need to unclutter your life
now you need to unclutter your life
seriously mentally in order just to gain
the perspective of what you are
subjected to either way and then you get
a sense of the escape from it so if you
if you if you properly understand I'm
subject to death you wouldn't be
searching for it would be inconceivable
and you even though you can get a hint
of that you know like when you get sick
because you were careless you were
eating crappy food or whatever else and
then there's a bit of a scare
you're real now for a week you couldn't
get out of the bed because now do you
know the stakes are high you feel it
inside is their sense of edges then you
recover and completely that context of
the intelligence chief I'll be careful
next is gone there you go you're doing
it again
because the mind is so fickle and mine
is fickle because you keep it so because
you you you basically you're not
reaching ahead you you're not trading it
you're not training against it you're
just giving into it and that's that's it
that's it's gonna bring to its increase
you're cultivating weakness
so that's all like like it's it's
doesn't matter if you're an absolute
beginner or if you've been practicing
for whatever decades but reading the
suttas and so on that is the context
that that remains unchanged and then you
should remain clarifying and running in
and maintaining or protecting it if you
developed it properly what you're
subjected to it and because that means
impossible to own that means like home
ownership after me
death means things that I own are
actually rooted in that which I can't on
so even if you're just just start your
Buddhism that's your practice keep the
precepts they will basically train you
in strength of restraint because if you
don't and then you start thinking about
this death and stuff well you might be
flying left and right in terms of things
you decide to do or run but now you've
said no to that type of engagement with
sense objects and you start clarifying
what you are subjected to then you will
be able to withstand anxiety sense of
urgency all these things without like
panicking and giving into to the
ridiculous actions of even madness and
so on but it's not optional there is not
a way then the delay the way of the
divine messengers that the Buddha
described is just whether you're gonna
equip yourself to be able to withstand
their way or not that's why I do what I
said sometimes so much progress is
painful someone else's isn't but it's
the same way it has to be the same way
whether you gonna suffer on account of
it or not is whether you can take it or
not
so even even if somebody is not
interested in the complete freedom from
suffering and hardship a layman but
still values the Buddhist teaching
that's your practice keep the precepts
and whatever you engage from the moment
you wake up you want me to go to sleep
try and have it against the backdrop of
and then everything will be well it will
even out even as a layperson who still
engages with family centrality
duties distraction it was significantly
even out your desires your passions will
even are because you do you refuse to
give in completely you keep at least one
percent of your decision to engage have
it against the fundamental context that
fundamentally things will be taken away
cannot be money that's basically
beginning of wisdom
even for a householder and you could see
how different that is like actively
thinking the thoughts of the context
that you're subjected to as opposed to
having your practice of just mindlessly
watching your nostrils for an hour a day
and then go about carelessly giving in
to desire and everything else because
you've done your duty now you don't have
to watch your hamster's although you
don't need to meditate you know because
this would be the meditation it's gonna
instead of this is when I do it it's
done all the time
literally putting things in the right
perspective how can you put something
perspective if you have no perspective
how can you gain perspective unless you
start investigating where the
perspective is let's in like if you're a
monk and come into the whole life
through his practicing whatever you're
about to do whatever you're doing
against the book you might not live
through this so it's a valid thought
it's a very context so could you say
that cellulite persons meditation could be
cellulite persons meditation could be
just thinking about clarifying
there is a samadhi without sati and sati
as we said it's recollecting the right
context so that's your Samadhi in that context
so that's your Samadhi in that context
it becomes less changeable or harder to
lose you can say you have Samadhi so
yeah absolutely
your practice of Samadhi and
concentration should be practice of
recollecting the right context which
causes the death context of a context
that is impossible to own the I organ
it's impossible to own the nose organ
and so on like if I can open these eyes
okay any sight sound and it's asides
they come through it or any sound how
can that possibly be mind when excites
any conceivable without a necessary
based survives functioning eyes think
about that feel it
a lot of sense of urgency allow it to
new and the restraint will become
effortless or certainly it will require
less effort
why because you realize by not engaging
I'm not exposing myself to risk of death
of losing or being that's what good a
compared going down the path of
sensuality is like climbing up the tree
to eat the mangoes at the top and then
expose yourself to risk of falling down
somebody chop in the tree millions the
reason can happen to that tree unless
you come down you will suffer on account
of them if you come down
doesn't matter if somebody cuz it cuts
the trees there's a man if somebody
burned the whole cinnamon out I lost
desiring what you move is there he will
not affect me you have that job yeah
studied mindfulness as in recollected
nests of the backdrop the right right
bank the right context and Samadhi is
maintaining it in protecting it and that
would result in fully understanding it
so a mindfulness there was obviously the
result of your of your restraint not
engaging by default the thought to have
a watch a movie I watch a movie sense
restraint so sila through that
mindfulness bring somebody just fully
establish this now the context remains
enduring despite was happening around
you the context doesn't need to change
that's the whole point
you only need to protect it basically
you protect it from yourself you protect
the context from you a band using your
context so once you stop doing things
they would interfere with the context
that's highly protected and the natural
result of that is fully understanding of
that context and fully understanding of
things what you used to do and how you
used to do them in order to basically
avoid face in the context when that
context is always in very steady then
you can't dictate
decisions in the future then you don't
need to do an exercise now I will not go
and engage with non engagement will be
automatic so Cielo bring Samadhi brings punya just
so Cielo bring Samadhi brings punya just
that's how it works yeah it's the in
either way Saffy is there but he
collected and so the context is there
then steady for Silla and necessary for
Somali necessary for Vanya so whatever
happens in mind something comes up but
is there a possibility building project
if you got the backdrop I'm going to die
tomorrow you can engage what if you
exactly oh you can engage and literally
like on a daily basis so to speak you
don't need to make that decision that
every day I will evaluate and ready
engage with it no just make a decision
to not lose the context that you might
not live through means whenever you end
up being engaged it's gonna be at the
arm's length and you'll be doing that
which is actually practically important
exactly passionate blind sort of self fueling
passionate blind sort of self fueling
ambition yeah they will become
inconceivable yeah the Samadhi
because a picker with some on to develop
the seasonings as they really are
mm-hmm what does this using really are
the aggregates of the senses sure yet
because they are already like that yeah
but you announce that the contacts is
now certainly not having the right
context means having the wrong context
yeah there's nothing in between which
means wrong context will be obscuring
how things are and that's exactly what
the Maura says but no decisions this is
mine and the mind is there you're
affected by and that's why the mother
controlled you and Maura himself cannot
see anything other than ownership which
is why so through through mother's
ownership three mothers domain you
understand the nature that domain and
that's why you stop owning it the mother
says even my path you will not see
exactly does mean how I used to be no
all it passed is understood against the
same bank of futures understood that's
right there are there is no more wondering
there are there is no more wondering
about it samsara because you understood
the aggregate changes to the framework
there is impossible to own
and that's what we said before you can't
lose what you recollect it accidentally
so if you recollect the context of that
correctly you don't know you recruit is
there all you need to do is keep a
corner of your eye on what you're about
to do next
now that you're doing but what you're
planning to do you're always planning
something to do it's always implicit
possibility of extending what I'm doing
now or whatever has to be there that's
what you keep an eye on that's how you
protect that that doorway okay so I am
subject to death so what am i doing I'm
sitting here oh now I'm giving in to
such and such thoughts essential nature
or nature bill will oh you can only do
that by choosing to do it which means
then choosing to turn away from the
context of death so if you don't make
the choice to turn away from it the tip
context of you being subjected and is
still there so you protect it by not
intentionally throwing it away and the
clearer that becomes the easier to
protect it it becomes because now you
think that all these things are
happening around them to me and these
random things can take away my
mindfulness know whenever mindfulness
taken away means there has been setting
in of desire aversion or distraction and
those things cannot not be intentional
sorry they're always intentional you cannot
they're always intentional you cannot
accidentally engage with sensual desire
it's on the level of the thoughts that
you've said yes to you cannot exit
enterely perform an act of ill-will or
accidentally distract yourself it's
always rooted in you choosing to do so
you stop choosing to do so you cannot
possibly obscure the context